If there's any snitches in the group, we
kill the snitches and they fire shots
out of a gun. Boom. Boom. And
everybody's kind of getting scared.
>> April 21, 2017. A group of men stand in
a remote field in the middle of Alabama.
>> It was nighttime and I am blindfolded.
I've been instructed to place my right
hand on the right shoulder of the person
in front of me in line because that
signifies brotherhood. The Brotherhood
is the Ku Klux Clan, the United States's
oldest, most notorious white supremacist
hate group.
This is one of their ceremonies. What
they don't know, one of them is an FBI
undercover agent, and he's no
lightweight, 6'4, 260 lb, covered in
tattoos. His nickname, Hillbilly Donnie
Brasco. He's gone undercover as a
contract killer, a contraband smuggler,
an arms dealer. He's put dozens of
people behind bars from drug dealers to
violent motorcycle gangs to pedophiles.
He's befriended and brought down biker
gangs and neo-Nazis. People who are
planning kidnappings, murders, and the
overall downfall of society.
>> And when he was saying, "We're going on
a camping trip," what he was saying is,
"We're going to kill somebody." And
everybody's screaming, "Death to your,
you know, f your Jewish God. Death to
America." And then somebody says, "If
there's any snitches in the group, we
kill the snitches." and they fire shots
out of a gun. Boom. Boom.
>> We drove all the way over to his ranch
in Tennessee and he told us everything.
This is the story of Scott Payne, the
redneck turned FBI agent who infiltrated
America's underbelly.
[music]
>> [music]
>> The majority of this video is based on
Scott Payne's book and podcast. Find the
links in the description.
>> What I saw was a watery image. It was uh
completely red and there was a demon
looking at me in that watery kind of
ripple image with a grin and long
crooked finger looking at me saying come
here smiling.
Scott is 14 years old and he's just seen
a demon. The year before his parents
divorced and Scott went down a dark
path. Consulting spirits, watching
diabolical horror movies, satanic
rituals, deals with the devil. That's
what brought him here. a friend's house
spending the night. They've had a small
amount of alcohol, but no drugs, no
hallucinogens.
>> I would do like these little vignettes
where I would pretend I was being
possessed by a demon or I was the devil
or whatever. I was on the couch and I
was doing this scene from a movie where
somebody is like being possessed by a
demon. And so I'm fighting in my voice
and then the demon voice comes in and
there's this battle and at the end the
demon wins and possesses the person. So
that's what I act like happened and I'm
laughing like the demon and I rolled
over.
>> It all started as a mock demonic
possession, but then he actually saw a
demonic figure and this was his breaking
point.
>> So let's just say after the demon scare,
I got Jesus scared back into me and that
was it. Not that the devil was down with
me, but I was down with him. [laughter]
>> Halloween night 2019. This is Scott on
his final major undercover mission. And
this is a goat. It was stolen and is now
at the center of a pagan ritual. It's
been nearly 35 years since [music]
Scott's first encounter with the devil.
But on this night, the devil is all
around him. And he's definitely not done
with Scott.
>> Now, we're all in a circle around the
goat. Somehow I ended up at the back of
it. I don't know how. It was bad luck on
my part, I guess. But I'm holding the
legs of the goat.
He's got this blade and he's bringing it
up and bringing it down in a practice
swing. Practice swing. Practice swing.
And finally, somebody says, "Just do
it." Eisen comes down with every bit of
force he's got and hits the back strap
of the goat. And I don't even know if it
broke a hair. I don't know if it's
because the backstrap's too thick. Uh
the blade was too dull, but he hit it
and all you heard the goat was just go
and I'm like, "Oh man, this is going to
get bloody and bad real fast."
>> The man swings again again. Nothing.
Finally, the blade is replaced with a
gun.
>> I said, "Whoa, whoa, whoa." And he's
like, "What?" I'm like, "Man, look at
what you're shooting at. We're all in a
circle around this thing." And then he
looks, puts a round right in the head of
the goat and it hits the ground.
So you think you're done. No, you're not
done. Now they slice the throat of the
goat and they fill up a cup full of
blood.
>> One of them pulls out a sheet of LSD. He
approaches each man one by one.
Basically, they would take the hit of
acid under their tongue, chase it with
the blood of the goat to signify the
sacrifice or or solidify the sacrifice.
>> Scott is one of the few who decline.
>> So, when it gets around to me at the
end, I'm looking at the blood and it's
already coagulated. It's all chunky and
clotty, and I'm looking at it going,
"Man, I really don't want to turn this
up and drink it. I mean, this is
disgusting." So, I dipped my fingers
deep into the blood, pulled them out,
and then sucked all the blood off my
fingers.
>> This is not the Ku Klux Clan. This group
is younger, better equipped, and
preparing for a blood bath. And not only
animal blood, but the blood of any human
who isn't one of them. Jewish and black
Americans, and anyone they consider
traders to the white race. They're by
far the most dangerous group Scott will
ever infiltrate. Unfortunately for these
tripping, bloodrinking white
supremacists, Scott Payne has other
plans. It's exactly the kind of thing he
spent the last 17 years working to
prevent.
I became an FBI agent in 1998 and uh by
2002 I'd already done some undercovers
for the FBI, but I wasn't yet certified
through the FBI undercover school. So I
finally got a slot.
>> September 2002, Quantico, Virginia. This
is the FBI Academy. If you make it
through the year-long application
process, if you pass the physical and
psychological assessments, the tests,
the polygraphs, the interviews, the
background checks, if you make it
through all that, you end up here in a
20we training program. If you get
through the 20 weeks, you become an FBI
agent. Scott's been here before. Now
he's back. About to start the training
program for undercover agents. Getting
admission to the program is hard enough.
Graduating is even harder. Only about
half the admittes make it through. It's
a two-eek school with no days off. We're
very big on sleep deprivation. Um you're
going through multiple scenarios of of
all shapes and sizes. Um and it's
[music] there's only 20 slots for the
class.
>> Others break down. They make missteps
during the high pressure scenarios. They
grow delirious and erratic from the lack
[music] of sleep. But Scott thrives. The
sleep deprivation, the relentless
roleplay, the grueling exercise. If
anything, he feeds on it. Meanwhile,
he's learning from his idols, legendary
FBI agents like Joe Piston, who spent 6
years undercover with the Bunano crime
family, but they don't always notice
him.
>> So, I remember Joe Piston coming to
speak and I was like a a kid in a candy
store, man. I'm like, "Oh my gosh, this
is Donnie Brasco. This dude did 6 years
undercover in the mafia and uh he's
teaching, but he has this he has this
thing where he keeps kind of wanting to
walk right up to the desk. So [laughter]
he kept stepping on my feet and I, you
know, I was trying to get out of his way
and then finally as he's teaching, he
just looks down at me and he says,
"Jesus, kid, either you got the biggest
feet I've ever seen or I can't see." And
he throws a couple of bucks on the desk
cuz he's like still in mafia mode. He
throws a couple He goes, "Hey, go get
yourself a shine on me." And uh I just
took my feet and shoved them under the
seat, man.
Joe Pistone may have scuffed up Scott's
shoes. What neither of them could have
known at the time is that Scott would go
on to fill Joe's.
The FBI Academy trains agents to take
down bad actors. More and more of these
criminals operate online. Scammers,
identity thieves, fraudsters, the list
goes on. Such criminals rely on your
personal data, your name, your phone
number, your email address, sometimes
even health related information. Most
people aren't aware that their data has
already been exposed and is actively
being sold by data brokers online.
Incogn helps solve this problem. Incogn
hundreds of data brokers and then
leverages data protection laws to have
your exposed data deleted. With their
unlimited plan, Incogn even offers
custom removals. If you find your
personal data exposed on eligible
website, you can submit the URL and your
team will request its removal. It may be
impossible to entirely disappear from
the internet, but Incogn can help you
become as invisible as possible. Incogn
is offering Fern viewers 60% off with
the code Fern TV. Just scan this QR code
or go to incogn.com/fernv.
Remember, no tool can guarantee 100%
removal. So, be careful with what you
share online.
>> So, once I was certified as an
undercover in the FBI, if you're looking
on paper, I really didn't jump out.
>> Scott doesn't have a fancy degree. He
doesn't speak any foreign languages. His
nickname is big country for obvious
reasons. So he begins to work as an
instructor at the school he just
graduated from. Unorthodox, but it got
him noticed by the right people.
>> I'm roleplaying in these scenarios and
people that are there who were senior
undercovers are watching cuz they're
trying to recruit for other cases. And
that's how my name started getting out
there.
>> So after months, there's finally a
possible assignment. One that Scott is
perfect for. Sure, he's a redneck with
almost no foreign language skills, not
suitable for many undercovers. But he
has something most other agents don't.
He doesn't need to pretend to be a hard-
misfit. He is one. He knows he'll feel
at home where he's about to go, but he
has no idea how close he'll grow to the
criminals he's been assigned to
infiltrate and how hard it will be to
turn on them.
>> People always have their own opinion of
what undercover work is. Um, some people
say it's acting, some people say it's
lying. Essentially, this is the
definition [snorts] of undercover work.
You are building relationships that
you're going to betray.
Scott is on a mission and his targets,
these men, have just arrived. They're
members of the Outlaws Motorcycle Club,
the main rivals of the Hell's Angels.
They've been implicated in drug
trafficking, prostitution rings,
moneyaundering, the list goes on. And
they're notorious for violence against
rival gangs. Infiltrating them is
exceedingly difficult. Scott Payne is
here to do just that. But there's a
problem. Part of the intelligence Scott
was given is wrong. He was told they
wouldn't be wearing their colors.
Obviously, they are. Scott has hoped to
strike up a casual conversation, letting
the topic of motorcycles arise
naturally. But these guys are
advertising their gang affiliation. He
can't just go up and say, "Hey, you guys
ride." His only choice is to make them
come to him. Luckily, another part of
the intelligence is right. This guy road
named Spanky loves to be the center of
attention. So Scott steals it. He works
the crowd. He tells jokes. He talks
loudly. He draws attention to himself,
making Spanky want [music] to steal it
back. Soon enough, Spanky asks where
Scott is from and sends him a drink.
>> Spanky's called me over. He's
introducing me to other people. And of
course, I'm getting more scrutiny. The
more people I meet, the more scrutinized
I am.
>> Everything seems to be going well, but
the real scrutiny happens somewhere
else. So I walk into the bathroom and as
I'm at the urinal and a lot of bars
there's like a little box in front of
the urinal plex of glass. It might be
flyers for a band coming up or a
stripper coming to town or something
like that. So I can see a little bit of
a reflection and I see this jacked big
dude come walking in [music] and I see
him looking at each stall and he's like,
"Okay, that's empty." I see him looking
under the stalls to make sure nobody's
in there and I'm watching this from a
reflection and then he comes walking up
right beside me and for a split second I
thought I'm getting jumped. I'm getting
jacked right here. And uh that didn't
happen. He says, "So what brings you to
Massachusetts?"
>> All undercover FBI agents have a legend,
a detailed madeup backstory that they
have to commit to memory. He's from deep
south Texas up in Massachusetts for
work. He loves Harley's and whiskey and
his name is Scott Callaway. As it so
happens, the guy grilling him in the
bathroom is also named Scott. [music]
Scott Town.
>> A lot of undercovers, you bond with
people, especially deep undercover long
term. But there's never been another
person I bonded with closer than Scott
Town.
>> For a year and a half, Scott gets to
know the outlaws. He drinks with them,
rides with them, fights alongside them.
He gains their trust. He becomes their
friend. They call him Tex. Scott's
legend may be a lie, but the friendships
are real. Scott Town becomes like a
brother.
>> He likes to drink. I like to drink. He
likes to fight. I like to fight. He
likes to ride and lift. I like to ride
and lift. We completed each other's
sentences. We were just kind of cut from
the same cloth.
>> They even both have a daughter who's the
exact same age. Scott Town is kind of a
doppelganger. The person Scott Payne
might have become had he not gone into
law enforcement. Another gang member,
Brian Devaga, aka closine, also becomes
a close friend of Scots. He said, "And
these guys are my brothers and I grew up
around them." He said, "But I really
don't have that many friends. Somebody
that I know would take a bullet for me
and that I would take a bullet for." And
in my mind, I'm looking at his face and
I'm going, "Oh, no, man. Don't say it."
And he looks at me and says, "You're one
of those guys."
Tomorrow is the big day.
Over the course of last year, Scott has
convinced the outlaws that he's a
high-ranking member of an international
theft ring. They begin running jobs
together. It begins small with insurance
fraud and vehicle trafficking. An outlaw
reports a motorcycle is stolen. He then
files an insurance claim while Scott
sells the motorcycle across the border.
A double win. Money from the insurance
company, money from the sale. They do
this again and again with motorcycles
and other vehicles. But tomorrow's job
is different. Some of the outlaws will
be serving as security during a major
drug deal, a gig arranged by Scott
himself. He's revealed that he has
connections with a Mexican drug cartel.
No surprise considering his line of work
and his proximity to the Mexican border.
The stakes are high. If they get caught,
they'll be looking at serious jail time.
And if something goes wrong during the
deal, the bullets will start flying. So,
when Scott is told to meet the outlaws
at their clubhouse, he's not surprised.
They probably want to go over the plan
one last time. Scott arrives. The place
is familiar. He's been here countless
times. He knows what's behind every door
in the building except one. Clothesline
leads him to that very door. Now he
realizes that something is wrong.
Scott is told to strip. They need to
check him for a wire. Because of the
stress of this happening, I forget my
middle name. I'm having an adrenaline
dump. And for anybody who's ever had it,
it can be any traumatic experience. But
I'm having auditory exclusion. So what I
hear sounds like I'm underwater. It's
going whoosh whoosh. So it's slow.
I need you to take all your clothes off.
It's slowing down. I'm getting time
dilation in my eyes. Everything I see is
in screen grabs. Click, click, click. I
can feel my heart beating through my
entire body. My hamstrings get rubbery.
Now, clothesline has instructed me to
take all my clothes off. Here's what
I'll tell you.
If I'm not wired, it's just an
embarrassing moment. I'm naked in a
small crawl space with two guys with
pistols. Problem is, I'm wired to the
hill.
>> But they don't find anything. Scott's
recording equipment is not taped to his
chest, but in his clothing. So, my
adrenaline starts settling and I'm
starting to come back to normal and I
think I'm done. And I get my pants back
up. I don't know if I have my boots on
yet or not. And then clos line grabs a
piece of clothing that I was wearing.
And that piece of clothing has a
recording device in it. And I'm watching
him and he starts grabbing the clothing
and he's going through it nice and slow
with his fingers. And I don't realize I
do it, but I there's an audible sigh.
You can hear me go
cuz I don't even know. I don't even know
I'm doing it. And he looks right at it
and misses it.
And uh I live to fight another day. I
live to fight another day.
Two moving trucks enter the parking lot
of the Brockton Holiday Inn. One is
filled with drugs. The other is filled
with money. A Mexican drug cartel is
selling 40 kg of cocaine and 1,000 lb of
marijuana to Canadian buyers. The
Mexicans aren't taking any risks.
They've arranged an American security
detail. The outlaws. Surveillance at
every entrance. Four men in the parking
lot there to provide protection, unload
the drugs, and count the money. Everyone
is armed and antsy. One false move and
all hell could break loose. The deal is
wrapped up quickly. The transfer is
complete. All the money's there. The
outlaws are particularly relieved. They
may be tough, but this is their first
time working with a cartel. Now they'll
get paid $15,000 for their services.
Scott counts out the cash. He did it. He
successfully tricked them. The cartel
FBI agents. The Canadians also FBI
agents.
8 months later, a hotel in Nevada.
Scott's been laying low, coordinating
his undercovers from afar. His outlaw
friends think he's going through a
divorce. [music] In reality, he's been
diagnosed as overassigned after
experiencing a severe stress related
panic attack. He's been ordered to take
a 6-month timeout. He's been teaching
during this time. His current class,
ironically enough, is called undercover
stressors. All the students have gone to
bed, but Scott's only just returned to
his hotel room. It's early 4 or 5:00
a.m. The drug deal back in November gave
the FBI all the evidence necessary to
arrest and imprison multiple outlaw
members, but the operation has continued
until today, the day of the takeown.
Scott doesn't think he'll hear from any
of them again, but then his phone rings.
It's Scott Town, and he's concerned.
He's heard some arrests were made, and
he wanted his friend to know about it.
He says he's going to take a shower and
gather more information. He'll report
back.
>> And the last words we spoke to each
other were, he said, "I love you,
brother." And I said, "I love you, too."
And that was the last words I spoke to
him. And probably about 45 minutes after
that, a SWAT team hit his house and he
went to jail.
>> In the end, 15 outlaws were arrested as
a result of Operation Roadkill. One of
them was sentenced to 21 years in
prison. Closine got 12 and a half years.
Scott Town 7. The Outlaws never saw
their friend Scott Callaway again.
The Ku Klux Clan emerged in the wake of
the American Civil War. From the very
beginning, they were racist to the core,
[music] reigning terror and death on
black Americans. In the late 19th
century, they fgged, tortured, and
lynched politically active black men,
raped their wives, shot their children,
and burned their schools. Historians
consider them to be America's first
terrorist movement. Today, the KKK
remains active, but only as a shadow of
its former self. Fewer members, less
influence. However, Burning Crosses is
still one of their favorite things to
do, and they've stayed true to their
roots. Naturally, as a terrorist
organization, they have to act in
secrecy. You might assume that
infiltrating them as an FBI agent is not
the easiest feat.
>> So, you may ask yourself, how do you
contact the United Clans of America?
Well, it turns out the group I was
looking at had a hotline.
>> Scott starts talking to a guy named John
Jack, a clansman whose passion for Jack
Daniels earned him this nickname. Scott
tells him he's got the number from a
group of bikers he met at a gas station.
It's a plausible story. Scott looks the
part and his time with the outlaws
taught him how to play it. Biker gangs
and white supremacists often run in the
same circles. Jack starts talking about
this rally that's coming up. Vendors,
burning crosses, country music, the
usual. but there's a problem.
>> He said, "I'm not going to lie to you,
Scott. I had a band lined up, but the
singer just got locked up, and I really
don't know what the hell I'm going to do
about music." And I thought, "This could
be my end." And I said, "Did I happen to
mention that I'm a musician and a
singer?" I said, "Well, I'll tell you
what I'll do. I'll bring my acoustic and
my PA system. When I get there, you can
come meet me by the car. I'll strum a
couple of tunes for you if you think I
suck." And he's like, "Oh, hell, this is
going to be great. It's going to be
great." Scott doesn't know that he just
signed up for something far more
sinister.
April 21st, 2017. It's the day of the
Kulux Clan rally.
>> I got lost multiple times until I
finally drove up on this empty, I don't
know, lot fenced in in the middle of
nowhere. But it wasn't hard to spot
because the Nighthawks, which would be
the clan members in all black, who were
the security force, are all standing at
the gate with guns. And a lot of these
people were felons. Scott's ready for an
interesting time. He's been to plenty of
biker gatherings, and perhaps this will
be similar. During his mission, Scott
will be taught the KKK's Constitution
and bylaws, studying the Black Clansman
Handbook, which he'll learn to refer to
as the Claren. He'll become familiar
with the original mystic insignia of the
clansmen. He'll learn this all in class
with a K so that he can pass the Kuno
test, a prerequisite to getting fitted
for a robe. Kuno stands for character,
honor, duty.
It's getting dark and he's been invited
to participate in a naturalization
ceremony. He has no idea what this
means, but all the newbies are doing it.
He'd stick out if he didn't. And that's
how he finds himself in the middle of a
field, blindfolded, holding the shoulder
of the man in front of him, a gesture
meant to signify brotherhood. They are
told to raise their right hands and
repeat an oath.
>> I do swear from this moment forward.
>> And then they tell us to get down on our
knees
>> to fostering the welfare of the white
race.
>> So I'm on my knees blindfolded
>> and further the work of America's
greatest movement. They take my
blindfold off and there's a Clue Clust
clan member in a green robe and he has
this sword and he kind of knits me.
>> The United Clans of America.
>> And then we all hug and there's like a
little bit of a celebration and I'm not
sure what happened. And then it hits me
as I'm walking to my truck. I'm like, I
think I just joined the damn clan. Yep,
that's what that was. So I got
naturalized in the clue clutch clan that
night. Scott's time at the KKK will end
up being relatively short-lived. The
case isn't really going anywhere. And
there's another group coming into focus,
a far more dangerous one.
>> In the FBI, we started encountering more
violent type extremism. Not not the KKK
types. We're talking advanced
neo-Nazism.
And it led me to an accelerationist
group called the base. The base mission
will provide to be far more extreme than
anything Scott has ever seen.
>> The network of violent white an
extremist group known as the base
violent neo-Nazi terrorist
>> paramilitary group called the base.
>> On August 11th, 2017, crowds of people
marched through the campus of the
University of Virginia in
Charlottesville, chanting racist and
anti-semitic slogans. They were
protesting the removal of a statue of
Robert E. Lee, the famous Confederate
general. The next day, they were met by
counterprotesters, and things quickly
turned violent.
Then they turned deadly. A white
supremacist drove his car into a crowd
of counterprotesters, injuring 35 people
and killing Heather Hayer. For some, the
Unite the Right rally was a wakeup call,
surprising proof that white supremacy
persists in America. To others, it was a
grim reminder and frightening evidence
that white supremacists were feeling
emboldened enough to come out of the
shadows. The first accelerationist group
emerged in 2015. They called themselves
Adam Buffin Division. They'd been
inspired by the writings of the neo-Nazi
James Mason, whose book Siege had become
a sort of Bible for accelerationists.
The book denies the Holocaust and
attacks homosexuals and Jewish people.
It also calls for organized violence,
specifically for the formation of terror
cells prepared to wage war against the
system. Initially regarded as fringe or
even cringe, accelerationism steadily
gained traction. By 2021, roughly 90% of
white nationalist groups identified as
accelerationist.
That same year, the US director of
national intelligence identified
racially motivated violent extremists as
the most lethal domestic terrorism
threat. More than other white
supremacist ideologies, accelerationism
insists on the importance of direct
violent action. The kind of action taken
by the people they call saints. Like St.
Terren for Brenton Tarant, the
Australian white supremacist who
attacked two mosques in Christ Church,
New Zealand. He killed 51 people. Or St.
Roof for Dylan Roof who killed nine
people, all black, during a church
service in Charleston, South Carolina.
This is the kind of action
accelerationists believe in. action that
will further destabilize society that
might finally lead to societal chaos.
They are explicit about this. ROF, for
example, said he'd hope to ignite a race
war. Failing that, though, the purpose
is to inspire more violence, which is
exactly what such attacks have done.
Scott Payne just signed up on Facebook.
He's about to publish another racist
post. His goal is to get banned,
but nothing happens. A fellow agent
points out that he doesn't have any
friends. He adds a few people and that
does it. He's promptly kicked off. Okay,
well done. Next up is Gab, a social
networking site well known for its
tolerant stance towards far-right users.
He participates in forms with names like
whites only. This will further elevate
his credentials. On July 15th, 2019, he
writes an email.
>> I've been seeing your stuff and I'm
definitely interested. Survival and
self-defense. I like it.
>> The next day, a ping.
>> Thanks for contacting the base. You can
learn more about us on our official Gab
account at the base. If you're
interested in joining, please provide
the following info to begin the vetting
process. The base is a white supremacist
neo-Nazi group. They were just founded a
year ago, and they are accelerationists
through and through. Their plan entails
assassinations, sabotage, and acts of
terrorism. Their targets are black
people, Jewish people, and anyone they
consider traitors to the white race.
>> They want to do guerrilla warfare
tactics. So, it's murdering people and
disappearing. It's poisoning a water
system, taking down a power grid,
derailing the train, anything that cause
chaos.
>> The idea is that after the collapse, the
group cells scattered across the world
will form white ethnostates led by white
supremacists. This event, Total Societal
Collapse, has a special name, the
Bugaloo.
Now Scott is trying to join them. They
ask for his name, White Warrior 88, and
his age, 44. Scott Payne is actually 48,
but he knows most base members are
between 18 and 25. He wants to seem as
young as possible. Sex, race, location,
military experience, fitness level,
special training, and organization
affiliations.
Here, his past undercover experiences
pay off. He mentions the clan and biker
gangs. So, here I am approximately for a
week or more. I'm emailing back and
forth to somebody with a Proton email
account and they're asking me all kinds
of questions about my ethnicity, what I
can bring to the table, what is my
history, and I laid out a story that I
was a old biker, shocker, and a former
skin head from South Carolina.
>> As Scott would find out later, the owner
of that email account was none other
than the founder of the base himself.
online. He's known as Norman Spear and
Roman Wolf. He's been on the public's
radar since 2018, but his true identity
is unknown. That is unless you're in the
FBI. Ronaldo Nazaro is 45, American,
born in New Jersey. He'd worked as a
contractor in Iraq for the Department of
Justice. Now he's in Russia, but is
2019. You can organize neo-Nazis into a
network of accelerationist insurgents
from just about anywhere. The email
exchange continues for less than a week.
Then Scott is invited for a phone
interview. It's supposed to take 30
minutes but ends up lasting an hour. Now
both Scott and the base have a 24-hour
grace period. After that, Scott will
need to make the decision. Does he truly
want to join?
>> I pass the test and they bring me in.
And they asked me, "Hey, where are you
located?" And I said, "In East
Tennessee." And they said, "The closest
sale to you is in North Georgia."
>> That's where Scott will have to pass one
final test, an in-person vetting
session.
August 2, 2019, Rome, Georgia. To Scott,
the men look more like boys. He knows
that one of them is the leader of the
base's Rome cell, but that's it. They
tell him to step out of his truck. Scott
isn't wearing a wire. He knows they'll
check.
But hidden in his truck is a tracking
device put there by his case team. As
long as Scott is near his truck, his
team will be able to find him. I step
out um you know shake hands or whatever
and he says, "Hey, I need you to put
your phone in airplane mode." And I
said, "Okay." He pulls out this wand
thing that I'd never seen before. It
looked like a geer counter. It had a big
triangle card in it, lights all over it.
He wands me and I pass cuz I'm fine. I
don't have anything. Then he starts
wanding my truck. No big deal until he
starts going to the back driver's side
of my truck, which is where the case
team placed my tracker. That thing he's
holding his hand starts going crazy. The
closer he gets to the back of the truck,
it starts beeping, beeping, beeping,
beeping, beeping, beeping. I see colors
going on it. I'm like, "Oh no, man. It's
picking up the tractor."
>> Scott braces for a fight. He's alone.
His team knows where he is, but they
have no idea something is wrong.
But he gets lucky. The other guy wonders
if the device is picking up the power
lines
>> and he walks over and it goes crazy and
he's like, "Damn it." Yeah. Whatever. He
says, "Yeah, it's the power lines. Hey,
follow us to another location."
>> Scott has to act fast. He has to get the
tracker deactivated.
>> And I'm calling the case team and I'm
like, "Hey, you need to shut that
tracker off." And at first they're like,
"Well, we can't shut it off." And I'm
like, "You have to shut it off." And
they're like, "Well, if we shut it off,
we're not sure. What if we can't get it
back on and we lose you?" I said,
"Here's what I'm telling you. Whatever
they have is picking up the tracker. If
you don't shut it off, this is going to
be a very fast undercover cuz it's going
to be over as soon as we get to where
we're going."
>> They arrive at an abandoned concrete
plant.
>> And I'm thinking to myself, "Oh, this is
great. How many movies have I seen where
somebody's killed in an abandoned
concrete plant? I hope they got the
tracker off. They pull out the wand.
They won me
and I I passed.
>> Scott is in. By this point, Scott's been
around the block, the Outlaws, the Kulux
Clan, but nothing could prepare him for
what comes next.
Scott has been with the base for over 2
months now. As a boy, he loved camping
with his parents and friends. He'd
explore the woods, go fishing, but the
camping trip he's just been invited to
isn't like the ones he used to go on.
The list of things to bring contains
some unusual items, weapons, ammunition,
and the same kind of camouflage. Flect
tarn worn by the German military. This
is no ordinary camping trip. This is a
hay camp, an extended training session
to prepare members for the bugaloo.
Hand-to- hand combat, weapons drills,
grappling. By [snorts] now, Scott has
attended a number of similar training
sessions, but this one is different.
It's longer, 3 to 4 days, and it's
bigger with base members coming in from
around the country, Texas, Alabama,
Michigan, Delaware. He's familiar with
many of the men he'll be camping with.
At least he knows most of their online
pseudonyms. Can't go back, is Punish
Snake, Dimma, Big Siege, Zumnat, all
from out of state. And of course, he
knows his fellow Georgia cell members,
Helter Skelter, and Pestilence, who
vetted Scott back in August with the
cell leader himself.
TMBB, the militant Buddhist. Everyone
knows Scott by his code name, Pill
Horse. When you're an undercover agent,
some cliches are true. Scott has learned
to expect the unexpected. Yet, he fails
to expect what would happen at the
Halloween hate camp. I wake up to a
pounding on my window. Pale horse, pale
horse, you got to wake up. You got away.
I'm like, "What's up, man? What's going
on?" They're like, "Hey, you got to get
out here and see this." I've been doing
undercover since 1996 at this point. And
I have never been with a group of people
where I had to burn Bibles, burn
American flags. [music] I damn sure
wasn't part of a group that went out and
stole a goat and we sacrificed it at a
pagan ritual and drank its blood. And I
did all that in 3 days with these guys.
>> After they decapitated the goat, the
group comes together for a barbecue.
They roast the goat over an open fire
and have it for dinner. All of this, of
course, while tripping balls.
It's impossible to know what blossomed
in their brains that night, what
hallucinatory horrors they saw. If their
drug field fantasies were anything like
their sober ones, then they dreamed of
death and destruction, of killing black
Americans, Jews, anti-fascists, and
communists, of the bugaloo. Scott has
become upsettingly familiar with these
fantasies and with the beliefs that
produce them. Behind each pseudonym is a
young man, and within each young man is
a darkness. The militant Buddhist real
name is Luke Lane. If the bugaloo
requires it, he says he could kill his
dad. Pestilence is Jacob Codly. He
believes Hitler is still alive. Michael
Helterbrand, aka Helter Skelter, says
he'd have no problem killing a commie
kid. Punish Snake, a former Canadian
soldier who'd been doxed by an
undercover journalist, gets emotional
talking about it, but he knows he'll
have to kill his ex- fiance when the
Bugaloo kicks off. She's half black.
Scott Payne records all of this and as
he earns their trust, he records more.
>> And we did more and more trainings
through that Saturday. But by that
Saturday night, we went back down to the
holy site and had a bonfire. And that's
where the American flags were burned.
That's where holy Bibles were set on
fire and everybody's screaming, "Death
to your, you know, f your Jewish God.
Death to America." And when that
training camp ended, that's when I
advanced even more in them trusting me.
And that's when TMBB and Pestilence
started bringing me in on murder plots
that they had.
>> It's more than 2 months later and Scott
is back at TMBB's farm, the 100 acre
property where the Halloween hate camp
took place. For the last few weeks, TMBB
has been talking about another camping
trip, but he's been ky. He doesn't want
to share information via chat. Scott has
convinced him to meet. He wants details.
It turns out the camping trip isn't a
camping trip. It's a hit job.
>> PMBB creates a separate chat room called
the camping trip. And when he was saying
we're going on a camping trip, what he
was saying is we're going to kill
somebody.
>> Their target is an active Antifa couple
in the Georgia area.
>> It was going to be me, TMBB,
Pestilence, and Helter Skelter. and we
were all going to make entry into the
house. TMBB wanted me to go with him to
kill everybody while Helter Skelter
would be covering out the window to make
sure no cops were coming and stuff like
that or help. And then Peslence was
going to set the house on fire. But in
the planning of everything, at one point
Helter Skelter says, "Hey, if you don't
mind, I'd like to pop my cherry on this
one." That confused me cuz it means
something completely different to me.
And I'm like, "What do you mean?" and he
said, "I would like to actually put a
bullet in somebody's head as well."
>> After casing the house, they begin the
next phase of the murder plot planning.
>> It was pretty extensive. Like you go to
a camping site, we leave everything
digital, everything, phones, everything.
There we go scrub ourselves at a pay by
the hour motel. We tape our pants to our
shoes, our gloves to our shirts.
um Vaseline on eyebrows and facial hair.
So, this is all to avoid leaving DNA um
for law enforcement. At one point, TMBB
had done research and he said that he
read that the first time somebody kills
somebody, they lose control of their
Bibles. So, he was suggesting that we
all wear adult diapers. I didn't tell
him that I'd killed somebody before, but
I told him I think I'm okay. I don't
need any diapers.
I was just as shocked when I got brought
in on this murder plot as most people
were. But while this is going on, the
Baltimore sale, which is can't go back
in Eisen and [music] Punish Snake, are
planning to go to this Second Amendment
gun rights rally in Virginia that they
thought was going to be the kickoff of
the Bugaloo and the D-Day, the race war.
Their idea was they knew you're going to
have a bunch of second amendment people
there, militias, 3enters, you're going
to have cops, you're going to have
protesters. What if you pop a couple of
rounds into that crowd? Nobody know
who's shooting at who and everybody
starts shooting each other. That could
be the set off.
>> Scott and his team know they have to
stop him and there's no time to lose.
The Pro Firearms Rally is on January
20th, 2020, just a few months away. They
jump into action. The next weeks are a
flurry of activity, meeting,
coordinating, and planning.
Finally, the day of the bus arrives.
>> It's a [music] Wednesday and I'm in
Rome, Georgia. I pick up Luke, who's
TMBB, to go to lunch and we pull out and
as I'm driving down the road, I knew
what my ruse was going to be. I was
going to say something was wrong with
the truck, but sure as you know what,
the truck made some loud sound I've
never heard. I didn't hit anything.
Something just went and I was like, "Did
you hear that?" He's like, "Yeah." And I
go, "Man, if my if my brake calipers are
frozen again, I'm going to be cuz that
did happen." So, I took a left out of
his neighborhood pre-planned by the SWAT
team. And I pull up tight to a fence.
And as I go, "Hey, I'm going to get out
and check the truck." So, I'm walking
around the back of the truck. Another
vehicle pulls up. He doesn't know who
they are. I know who they are. They're
part of the case team. And the guy says,
"Hey, man. You need any help with that?"
And I look up and I'm like, "Oh my gosh,
I can't believe it's you. What are you
doing in Rome, Georgia?" He goes, "What
are you doing here?" I was like, "Man, I
haven't seen you." And and as I'm doing
that, there's the distraction. Here
comes a Bearcat with a SWAT team over
the hill barreling down the hill. But
Luke's looking at me, not at the car
coming. And when that thing is coming, I
jump in the back of the agent's truck
and I'm like, "Go, go, go." And you
could hear the SWAT team giving
commands. And and luckily, the arrest
went down without an incident. The next
morning, SWAT teams arrested at K can't
go back and punish Snake.
>> Essentially, we kind of we kind of tore
down the base.
Luke Lane, aka TMBB, was sentenced to 6
years in prison. Jacob Carterly,
pestilence got 13. William Bilbro is
five. Patrick Matthews, Punish Snake,
and Brian Lemley, can't go back 9 years.
According to a recent Guardian article,
the base is enjoying a resurgence. Its
founder, Ronaldo Nazaro, continues to
live in St. Petersburg.
Scott retired in June 2021. At his
retirement ceremony attended by friends,
family, colleagues, and top FBI brass,
June 30th was named Scott Payne Day.